Guide to the Donald Oenslager Collection of Edward Gordon Craig
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Donald Oenslager collection of Edward Gordon Craig
1881-1975
GEN MSS 424
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.45
(14 boxes) + 2 broadside folders
Collection contains materials collected by Donald Oenslager documenting the life and career of Edward Gordon Craig, including correspondence, writings, artwork and materials related to theater design, photographs and subject files. Correspondence includes letters between Craig, Isadora Duncan and Paris Singer, letters between Oenslager and various individuals concerning his collection and interest in Craig, and third party letters. Writings include holographs, typescripts, clippings and reviews of writings by Craig, Oenslager and others, primarily related to Craig, including articles by Sheldon Cheney and Ellen Terry, and typescript fragments of Isadora Duncan's My Life. Artwork and theater design contains originals and reproductions of woodcuts, etchings and drawings by Craig and others, as well as an engraved woodblock of the alphabet, a model for Craig's stage screens, prints of two etchings by Francisco Goya and a hand-colored lithograph of Ellen Terry by Pamela Colman Smith. Photographs include pictures of Craig, Ellen Terry, and others. Subject files contain newspaper clippings, theater programs of productions acted in or designed by Craig, materials related to Craig's publications The Mask and The Page, and other papers.
Oenslager, Donald, 1902-1975
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Donald Oenslager, 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile materials in boxes 12-14 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files. One original color slide came with the collection. A photographic print of the image exists in the papers and the original slide has been stored separately.
EDWARD GORDON CRAIG, 1872-1966
Edward Gordon Craig was born in England on 16 January 1872, the son of the actress Ellen Terry and the architect E. W. (Edward William) Godwin. In 1878, at the age of six, he made his first stage appearance in a production of Olivia, by W. G. Wills. He studied at Southfield Park and Bradfield College, and was a member of Henry Irving's theater company at the Lyceum Theatre in London beginning in 1889.
In 1893, Craig married May Gibson, and moved from London to Uxbridge. Under the influence of the artists James Ferrier Pryde and William Nicholson, he learned the art of wood-engraving, and began his career as a graphic designer. In 1893 he directed and designed his first stage production: Alfred de Musset's On ne badine pas avec l'amour. Around this time he also published a magazine, The Page, consisting mostly of his own engravings, and in 1899 published a book of woodcuts with accompanying verses entitled Gordon Craig's Book of Penny Toys.
Craig's career as a stage designer continued to evolve as he collaborated with Martin Shaw in 1901 and 1902 productions of Dido and Aeneas, The Mask of Love and other plays. In 1904 Craig traveled to Berlin to work with the Lessing Theatre, and in 1905 he published his most famous essay, The Art of the Theatre, which was later expanded and republished as On the Art of the Theatre. In Germany he met the dancer Isadora Duncan, with whom he had a brief but intense affair, ending in 1906. Duncan persuaded the theater producer Konstantin Stanislavsky to invite Craig to Moscow, and there he designed an important 1912 production of Hamlet. In 1913, Craig fulfilled a longtime dream by founding his School for the Art of the Theatre in the Arena Goldoni in Florence, however, it closed shortly thereafter at the outbreak of World War I.
Over his long career Craig became known as an important innovator in theater design, popularizing a modern, minimalist style in contrast to the more extravagant style of his mother's age, and his writings, artwork and design had an enormous impact on twentieth-century theater. His publications include the theatrical periodical The Mask (1908-1929), and the books Books and Theatres (1925), Ellen Terry and Her Secret Self (1931), Nothing, or, the Bookplate (1924), The Theatre - Advancing (1919) and his autobiography, Index to the Story of My Days (1957). He spent the last years of his life in the south of France, and died there in 1966.
DONALD OENSLAGER, 1902-1975
Donald Mitchell Oenslager was born in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania on 7 March 1902. After graduating from Harvard in 1923, he spent several years working as an actor, appearing in a 1924 production of Desire Under the Elms at the Greenwich Village Theatre, and working at the Provincetown Playhouse. His first stage design was for a ballet titled Sooner or Later in 1925, and he soon began a prolific career in theater design that spanned the 1920's through the 1960's.
Oenslager wrote and edited several books on theater design, including Scenery Then and Now in 1936 and Notes on Scene Painting in 1952, and served as a member of the U.S. National Commission for Unesco and many local and national theater and arts organizations. He also served in the U.S. Air Force from 1942-1945, and from 1925 on he was a member of the faculty of the Yale School of Drama. He cited Adolphe Appia and Edward Gordon Craig as the inspirations for his work in theater design, and maintained collections of material related to the two designers, both of which are held by the Beinecke Library at Yale.
Scope and Contents
The Donald Oenslager Collection of Edward Gordon Craig consists of materials collected by Oenslager documenting Craig's life, career and his contribution to the art of the theater. The collection contains correspondence, writings, artwork, materials related to theater design, photographs, clippings, theater programs and other papers. The materials have been arranged into five series: Correspondence, Writings, Artwork and Theater Design, Photographs, and Subject Files, and span the years 1881-1975.
Series I, Correspondence (1911-1975), contains letters to and from Edward Gordon Craig, Donald Oenslager, and several third-party correspondents, particularly Isadora Duncan and members of her family. The Edward Gordon Craig correspondence contains original letters written by Craig, photocopies of transcripts of many letters from Craig to the printer Guido Morris, and a printed version of a letter from Morris to Craig. The Donald Oenslager correspondence contains letters from booksellers, Craig scholars and others concerning Oenslager's collection of Craig materials, and other letters related to his interest in Craig. Also included in this series are letters between Craig, Augustin Duncan, Isadora Duncan, Paris Singer and others regarding their plans to open a dance theater in Paris for Isadora Duncan. Other third-party correspondence contains letters by Max Beerbohm, George Bernard Shaw, and others.
Series II, Writings (1906-1972), contains holographs, typescripts, and clippings of writings by Edward Gordon Craig, including many newspaper articles, proofs and reviews of several of his books, and other writings. Also included in this series are writings by Donald Oenslager, including drafts of his version of Aristophanes' The Birds, and a scrapbook with notes regarding a project for Wagner's Ring cycle. Writings of others include corrected typescripts of a portion of Isadora Duncan's My Life, an article about stage decoration by Ellen Terry, and other writings, primarily about Craig.
Series III, Artwork and Theater Design (1900-1972), contains postcards, clippings, reprints, and original woodcuts, drawings and etchings by Craig, including a two-volume limited edition of his etchings and an original wood block of the alphabet. Also included are designs for two theater productions, a model of Craig's innovative folding stage screens, and a photocopy of his patent application for the screens. Artwork by others contains prints of two etchings by Francisco Goya, a reproduction of a drawing of Craig by Claude Marks, a hand-colored lithograph of Ellen Terry by Pamela Smith Colman and an unidentified sketch of several waiters.
Series IV, Photographs (1888-1960), contains photographs of Edward Gordon Craig and others. Many of the photographs of Craig were taken by David Lees, Craig's son with Dorothy Nevile Lees, his collaborator on The Mask. Each of these photographs includes a negative print along with the positive. Other photographs include pictures of Craig by other photographers, pictures of Craig's Macbeth production, one photograph of Ellen Terry, one of Terry and her family taken by Lewis Carroll, and one photograph of an unidentified exhibit of Craig materials.
Series V, Subject Files (1881-1972) includes newspaper clippings, materials related to an exhibition of "Architects in the Theatre, 1500-1900," catalogs and posters for exhibitions of Craig material, papers related to The Mask and The Page, theater programs of productions in which Craig performed, directed or designed, and other papers including lists of books by and about Craig, book prospectuses and sales catalogs of Craig material.
Theater -- Production and direction; Theaters -- Stage-setting and scenery; Wood-engraving; Etchings (prints); Lithographs; Photographic prints; Wood blocks (printing blocks); Woodcuts (prints); Etchings; Set designers; Cheney, Sheldon, 1886-1980; Craig, Edward Gordon, 1872-1966; Duncan, Isadora, 1877-1927; Goya, Francisco, 1746-1828; Oenslager, Donald, 1902-1975; Singer, Paris Eugene; Smith, Pamela Colman; Terry, Ellen, Dame, 1847-1928
- Correspondence, 1911-1975; Series I; 0.4; (1 box)
  - EDWARD GORDON CRAIG CORRESPONDECE
    - Hone, Joseph [Maunsell?], [1922?], 1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Junge, Ewald, 1953 Jul 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - King, F. A., [1917?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Morris, Guido. Photocopies of transcripts of letters, 1946-54 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Morris, Guido, "Second Printed Letter of Guido Morris to Edward Gordon Craig," printed version of letter dated 27 July 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Partington, Mr.
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Series II, Writings, Writings of Edward Gordon Craig, "Booksellers (1) in Italy," Box 3, folder 100
    - Singer, Paris
      See: Box 1, folder 39
    - ----, David, 1941 Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - DONALD OENSLAGER CORRESPONDENCE
    - A. & B. Booksellers, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes: Letters from Benjamin Blom
      Includes: Appraisal of DO's collections of EGC and Adolphe Appia
    - Archer, Ken
      See: Series II, Writings, Writings of Others, "Gordon Craig Creates and Translates..." Box 4, folder 121
    - B. F. Stevens & Brown Ltd., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Beauchamp Bookshop Ltd., 1957-60 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Blom, Benjamin
      See: A. & B. Booksellers, Box 1, folder 8
    - Craig, Ellen Gordon, 1966 Dec (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Fletcher, Ifan Kyrle, 1962 Oct 22 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      See also: Series II, Writings, Writings of Edward Gordon Craig, Ellen Terry and Her Secret Self, Box 2, folder 77
    - Junge, Ewald, 1956-57 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      See also: Series V, Subject Files, Other Files, Book prospectuses, Box 7, folder 240
    - King, F. A., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - King, John V., 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Lees, David, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes: "Edward Gordon Craig: In Search of Theatre. Outline for a film project," by David Lees, typescript
    - Low, David, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - McGlinn, Frank C. P.
      See: Series V, Subject Files, Theater Programs, Macbeth, The American Theatre, Box 7, folder 227
    - Princeton University Library, 1966 Oct 25 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Includes: Photocopies of 3 letters from Douglas Ross to George C. Tyler, 1928, and a photocopy of a letter from EGC to "Miss Anglin," 6 September 1928, from the Princeton University Library
    - Rood, Arnold, 1962, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Letter of 1969 is on a card with a woodcut by EGC
      Includes: Typescript summary of DO's collection of EGC
      See also: Series III, Artwork and Theater Design, Wood block of the alphabet, Box 5, folder 146
    - Ross, Douglas
      See: Princeton University Library, Box 1, folder 18
    - Rosse, Herman
      See: Series V, Subject Files, Chapter One, Box 8, folder 265
    - Sheren, Paul, 1966, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Undated letter is on a card with a woodcut by EGC
    - Singer, Mrs. Cecil, 1961 Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Letter from DO regarding the correspondence about the proposed Duncan Theatre, which came to him from the Singers
    - Steegmuller, Francis, 1973 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Letter from Steegmuller regarding the correspondence about the proposed Duncan Theatre
    - Tice and Lynch, Inc., 1956 Jun 8 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - United Scenic Artists, 1961 Jan 23 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Includes: Invitation to the induction of EGC as an honorary member of the United Scenic Artists
    - ----, Herbert, 1957 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Unidentified, 1957, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - CORRESPONDENCE CONCERNING THE DUNCAN THEATRE
    - Bantock, Granville
      - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Block, Henri
      - Delapalme, Pierre, 1912 Jul 6 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Duncan, Augustin
      - Murray, Gilbert, 1912 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        Includes: Copies of telegrams to Isadora Duncan from Murray and "Campbell," 24 August 1912
    - Duncan, Isadora
      - Bloch, Henri, 1912 Jun 19 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Delapalme, Pierre, 1912 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Murray, Gilbert, 1911 Sep 4 (Box 1, Folder 32)
        Includes: "Project to Produce Greek Plays," carbon typescript
      - Singer, Paris Eugene, 1912, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Unidentified, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Duncan, Raymond
      - Duncan, Elizabeth, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Lyon, Gustave
      - Unidentified, 1912, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Preston, Stanley
      - Johnson, R. E. Johnson. Carbon typescripts of letters, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Singer, Paris Eugene
      - Bloch, Henri, 1912 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Craig, Edward Gordon, 1912, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
        Includes: A draft proposal by Singer regarding the theater for Isadora Duncan
      - Duncan, Augustin, 1911-12, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
        Includes: "Project for the Production of the Alcestis of Gilbert Murray and Other Plays," carbon typescript
      - Duncan, Isadora
        See: Box 1, folder 33
      - Greffulhe, Elizabeth, comtesse, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - Huillard, Paul, 1912, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Mathios, L., 1912 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - Michel, F. H., 1912, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - Preston, Stanley, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Süe, Louis, 1912, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Unidentified
      - To the Préfet de Police. Application for permission to build the proposed Isadora Duncan theater, with reply[?]. Carbon typescripts, [1912?] (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - OTHER THIRD-PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Arnott, Brian
      - Hemdal, Janet, 1975 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Beerbohm, Max
      - Shaw, George Bernard. Holograph copy of an undated letter, with typescript copy, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Junge, Ewald, [n.y.] Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Leeper, Janet
      Rood, Arnold
      See: Series III, Artwork and Theater Design, Wood block of the alphabet, Box 5, folder 146
    - Olivier, Laurence
      Junge, Ewald
      See: Series II, Writings, Writings of Edward Gordon Craig, "Letter to L. Olivier..." Box 3, folder 101
    - Shaw, Bernard
      - Terry, Ellen, printed version of letter from 9 November 1913, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Writings, 1906-1972; Series II; 1; (3 boxes)
  - WRITINGS OF EDWARD GORDON CRAIG
    - Articles
      - "The Actor and the Über-Marionette," printed version (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - "Between Two: The Arts of the Theater," clipping fragment of printed version of article about Eleonora Duse, 1929 Mar 2 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - "Bluff in the Theatre," clipping fragment of printed version, 1928 Jul 3 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      - "The Bottle Washers of Alexandre Dumas, Papa," clipping of printed version, The Graphic, 1926 Jun 12 (Box 2, Folder 56)
      - "The Christ in the Carpenter's Shop," clipping of printed version, The Sunday Times, 1960 Jul 24 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - "Early Failures: First Night of The Bells: Actor and Egoist," clipping of printed version, The Times Weekly Edition, 1929 Sep 26 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      - "The English Theatre in St. Ambrogio," clipping of printed version, The New Statesman, 1930 Jul 19 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      - "Gordon Craig and the Dance," special issue of Dance Index with articles by EGC, 1943 Aug (Box 2, Folder 60)
        Includes: "The Russian Ballet," "Margin Notes," "The Javanese Ballet," "Margaret Morris," "Balanchine's 'Apollo'," "Isadora Duncan: Studies for Six Dance Movements" and "Lady Diana Goes to the Ballet"
      - "Has the Stage Helped Us to a More Graceful Life?" clipping of printed version, The Daily Chronicle, 1928 Jul 4 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      - "Henry Irving: Friends at the Lyceum: The National Theatre," clipping of printed version (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - "Henry Irving: His Physical Features: Nature and Art," clipping of printed version (Box 2, Folder 63)
      - "Henry Irving: The First Night of The Bells: His Masterpiece," clipping of printed version, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 64)
      - "Italy's Unique Wedding Gift Books," clipping of printed version, The Graphic, 1924 Mar 29 (Box 2, Folder 65)
      - "A Letter to Eleonora Duse," clipping of printed version, Westminster Gazette, 1908 Nov 15 (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - "A Note on Great Theatres," clipping of printed version, The London Times, 1922 Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 67)
      - "On Creating and Destroying Lambranzi," proofs, corrected, [1929?] (Box 2, Folder 68)
      - "Playwright's Purge," clipping fragment of printed version, Boston Evening Post [?], 1931 Oct 7 (Box 2, Folder 69)
        Review of Modern Continental Playwrights by Frank Wadleigh Chandler
      - "Prescription for Recovery," clipping of printed version, The New York Times, 1935 Feb 3 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - "Reflections on the Irving-Shaw Controversy," clipping of printed version, The Listener, 1952 Jul 17 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      - "What's Wrong with the Stage?" clipping of printed version, The Daily Herald, 1920 Jun 30 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      - "Who Can Reform the Stage?" clipping of printed version, The New York Times, 1935 Sep 8 (Box 2, Folder 73)
      - "Wood-Engraving and the Theatre," clipping of printed version, The Graphic, 1922 Dec 23 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      - "The World, the Flesh, and the Devil in the Theatre," clipping of printed version, The Nation and Athenaeum, 1930 Jul 12 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Books
      - Books and Theatres, review, clipping of printed version, The New Statesman, 1925 Dec 12 (Box 2, Folder 76)
      - Ellen Terry and Her Secret Self, unbound gatherings. "15 copies on proof paper printed for the author", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 77-80)
        Includes: Letter from Ifan Kyrle Fletcher to DO, 18 April 1952, and notes by EGC, both regarding this copy of the book
      - Ellen Terry and Her Secret Self, reviews, clippings of printed versions, 1930-32, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 81)
        Includes: Clippings about the Bernard Shaw and EGC argument caused by the book
      - Fourteen Notes, reviews, clippings of printed versions, 1931, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 82)
      - Henry Irving, review, clipping of printed version, The Morning Post, 1930 Oct 1 (Box 2, Folder 83)
      - Index to the Story of My Days, proofs, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 84-86)
      - On the Art of the Theatre, proofs, corrected, 1911 Oct (Box 2, Folder 87-90)
        Includes: Dealer notes about the book and the proofs
      - On the Art of the Theatre, proofs of the preface and several pages, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 91)
      - On the Art of the Theatre, annotated proofs of illustrations, 1911 Oct (Box 2, Folder 92-94)
      - On the Art of the Theatre, reviews, clippings of printed versions, 1912-62, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 95)
      - A Production, review, clipping of printed version, The Daily Telegraph, 1930 Aug 26 (Box 2, Folder 96)
      - Scene, review, clipping of printed version, The Daily Telegraph, 1923 Nov 19 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      - The Tragedie of Hamlet Prince of Denmarke, by William Shakespeare, illustrated by EGC, review, clipping fragment of printed version, News Chronicle, 1931 Feb 6 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Other Writings
      - "Animadversions on Dancers," clipping of printed version, 1932 May 29 (Box 3, Folder 99)
        Review of A Short History of Costumes and Armour by Francis Michael Kelly and Randolph Schwabe
      - "Booksellers (1) in Italy," typescript, corrected, [1923?] (Box 3, Folder 100)
        Includes: Proofs of 2 woodcuts by EGC, and letters from EGC to "Mr. Partington[?]," 26 March 1923 and 16 June 1923
      - "Letter to L. Olivier from EGC. Paris. 1945," typescript with annotations by EGC, bound in colored paper cover (Box 3, Folder 101)
        Includes: 7 photographs of EGC, 1 photograph of Laurence Olivier as King Richard III, and 1 drawing by EGC
        Includes: Letter from Laurence Olivier to Ewald Junge, 17 May 1947
      - "Mr. Gordon Craig's Theatre. A Letter Reprinted from The Nation, October 4, 1913," clipping of printed version, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 102)
      - Untitled typescript, corrected, of EGC's talk about Henry Irving and Bernard Shaw, broadcast on the BBC, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - WRITINGS OF DONALD OENSLAGER
    - "American Theatre: 1860-1910"
      - Typescript, in Archives of American Art. Report on Conference IV: Needs and Opportunities for Re-evaluation in the Arts in America, 1860-1910, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 104-106)
    - These Modern Birds!
      - Holograph play and summary, with printed version of Aristophanes' play The Birds on verso of each page (Box 3, Folder 107-111)
      - Typescript play "adapted ... from The Birds of Aristophanes", 1928 (Box 3, Folder 112-114)
      - Typescript summary, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 115)
      - "A Projected Production of The Birds of Aristophanes," typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 116)
      - Scene designs, pencil on graph paper, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 117)
    - The Ring Project
      - "A Project for The Ring ," typescript, corrected, [1927?] (Box 3, Folder 118)
      - Scrapbook with printed pages of the libretto and music of Richard Wagner's Ring cycle, with notes in DO's hand
        Includes: "A Project for The Ring " clipping of printed version, Theatre Arts Monthly
    - Other Writings
      - Transcript of a paper on American theater read at a conference held by the Archives of American Art, typescript, corrected, 1962 Apr 7 (Box 3, Folder 119-120)
        Includes: Letter to DO from the Archives of American Art, 1 February 1963
        Includes: Outline entitled "American Theatre 1860-1910," typescript, corrected
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Archer, Ken
      - "Gordon Craig Creates and Translates Acting into a Visual Element in the Moscow Art Theatre's 'Hamlet'," carbon typescript, corrected with photocopied illustrations, 1972 Dec (Box 4, Folder 121-122)
        Written for a class taught by DO at at Hunter College
        Includes: Letter to DO from Ken Archer, 14 January 1973
    - Cheney, Sheldon
      - "Gordon Craig's Service to the Theatre, An Essay by Sheldon Cheney with a Few Additions by Edward Gordon Craig," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 123)
      - "Gordon Craig's Service to the Theatre," proofs[?], corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 124)